Finding Aid for Ameinu Detroit records, 1928-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ameinu Detroit records 1928-2009
Ameinu Detroit.
1 oversize folders
8.5 linear feet
2009128 Bd 2; UBDm
Southeastern Michigan branch of the Labor Zionist Organization of American, now renamed Ameinu Detroit; organizational files include minutes of the Detroit Council, topical files, administrative correspondence, financial records, some local branch materials, publications, and visual and audio materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the organization (donor no. 10229 ) in July 2009.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Detroit branch of the Labor Zionist Organization of American (Poale Zion) was established in 1906. The underlying purpose of the organization, according to one writer, was "the inner urge for a spiritual reconstruction" that would bring about the transformation of young people "estranged from the soil and manual labor through centuries of Diaspora life, into enthusiastic workers and farmers in the land of Israel."
Prior to World War II, the Labor Zionist Organization (Poale Zion) developed a fraternal order (the Farband), the Pioneer Women's Organization, the League for Labor Palestine and the Histadrut Campaign. And through a network of Jewish Folk Schools, summer camps, and Habonim (now Habonim Dror), a progressive Zionist youth organization (founded in 1935), the children of members and friends became acquainted with the goals and ideals of labor Zionism.
According to its articles of incorporation dated 1943, the Detroit Labor Zionist Institute was created to raise and collect money "for the purpose of establishment and maintenance of a center for the cultivation, promotion and advancement of Hebrew and Yiddish culture, literature and art; to conduct schools and classes for instruction in Hebrew and Yiddish religion, education, literature and drama; and to otherwise promote, cultivate and advance the social, cultural, recreational and educational welfare of Jews in the metropolitan area of Detroit."
In 1947 Detroit became one of the first branches of the Labor Zionist Organization to establish a Central Committee, the purpose of which was (1) to execute the directives and carry out the programs of the national organization and (2) to bring together for concerted action (particularly fund raising) the divisions of the Zionist Labor Movement. These divisions included the Habonim Youth Movement, the Detroit Farband City Committee, the Detroit Council of Pioneer Women and all of the city's local branches of the Labor Zionist Organization.
In its history, the organization has undergone several name changes following mergers and restructurings and in an effort to attract new members. In 1971, the Labor Zionist Organization (Poale Zion) joined with Farband and the American Habonim Association to form the Labor Zionist Alliance; and in 2004, LZA became Ameinu.
The record group includes documentation of both the Labor Zionist Organization and the Labor Zionist Institute. Some of the records date back to the early 1930s with the bulk of files dating from 1970. Included are minutes, topical files, correspondence, financial records, individual branch records, publications, and miscellaneous photographs, videotapes, and sound recordings. The record group documents the social and cultural programs and activities of one segment of Southeastern Michigan's Jewish community. Documented is the organization's fund raising activities, its interaction with other area groups, and its position on national and international issues.
Subjects:
Ameinu Detroit.; Jews--Michigan--Detroit Metropolitan Area.; Labor Zionism--Michigan--Detroit Metropolitan Area.; Labor Zionist Organization of America - Poale Zion.; Labor Zionists--Michigan--Detroit Metropolitan Area.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ameinu Detroit.; Jewish National Workers' Alliance (U.S.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Minutes and related material
  - Minute books 1933-1947, 3 volumes
    (in Yiddish)
  - Labor Zionist Alliance Council
    (earlier records are of the Labor Zionist Organization of American and of the Poale Zion Council; later records are of Ameinu Detroit; also includes some scattered minutes of the Executive Committee)
    - 1951-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1971-1994, 21 folders (Box 1)
    - 1995-1998, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 2003-2009, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Labor Zionist Institute
    - 1955-1957 (Box 2)
    - 1970-2004, 16 folders (Box 2)
- Topical file
  - Aaronson, Shlomo 1984 (Box 3)
  - Addison (Rabbi Howard A.) / Jeffry Mallow lectures 1985 (Box 3)
  - Administrative Committee 1991 (Box 3)
  - Afro-Asian Institute of Histadrut in Israel -- fund-raising lists 1991 (Box 3)
  - Announcements of upcoming programs, 1 folders (Box 3)
  - APRI / LZA Coalition (Box 3)
  - Blumenberg, Alex (president of Detroit LZA Council) 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - Cemetery plot list (Box 3)
  - Chavar (information for stories and related), 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - Condolence and get well messages 1977-1987 (Box 3)
  - Constitution, by-laws, and articles of incorporation of Detroit Central Committee and of the Labor Zionist Institute, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Detroit Yiddish Theatre (proposed) 1975 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Zionist Federation 1978-1986 (Box 3)
  - Dinitz, Simcha (lecture) 1982 (Box 3)
  - Endowment 1986-1989 (Box 3)
  - Eyal, Eli (lecture) 1982 (Box 3)
  - Friends of Labor Israel (Box 3)
  - Habonim Camp Tavor and related (Box 3)
  - Hagadda-Yom Ha'atzmaut (Box 3)
  - Histadrut (Israel Histadrut of Metropolitan Detroit) (Box 3)
  - Itonenu (newsletter of the Detroit Council), 1980s-2008, 5 folders (Box 3)
    (include mark-up galleys of issues, background information, copies of the newsletter, and newsletters of related organizations)
  - Jewish Community Council (mainly newsletters and announcements of programs) 1983-1987, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Jewish Film Festival 1982-1985, 5 folders (Box 4)
    (include announcements, financial reports, correspondence, and related material)
  - Labor Zionism miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Membership dues and forms 1981-1990s, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Michigan Trade Union Council for Histadrut (Dick Cordtz dinner) 1987 (Box 4)
  - Mid-West Camp Habonim, ca. 1961- circa 1980, 1 folders (Box 4)
  - Midwest Ideological Seminar 1989 (Box 4)
  - Midwest Regional Seminar
    - 1984 (Box 4)
    - 1985 (Box 4)
    - 1987 (Box 4)
    - 1988 (Box 4)
      (include newsletters)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - National Office (correspondence and other materials) circa 1984-1996, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Pollard, Jonathan (Michigan Committee for Freedom for Jonathan Pollard) 1991 (Box 5)
  - Program Committee 1988 (Box 5)
  - Property: Schaefer Highway; Arlington Park; and Middlebelt Road (Box 5)
  - Scholar in residence (Shlomo Gazit) 1999-2000 (Box 5)
  - Scholarships and awards (Box 5)
  - Shrodeck, Issy (political action committee) 1982-1984 (Box 5)
  - Special Fund Campaign 1982-1989, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Spicehandler, Ezra (Box 5)
  - Tributes and memorials
    - Naimark, Helen and Norman (Box 5)
    - Noveck, Evelyn (Box 5)
  - United Jewish Folk Schools (Box 5)
    (include photographs)
  - Vigil activities 2002 (Box 5)
- Correspondence
  - 1982-1997 2003-2009, 17 folders (Box 6)
- Financial records
  - Labor Zionist Assembly: Financial statements and related 1978-1996 (some gaps), 8 folders (Box 7)
  - Labor Zionist Institute
    - Financial statements and related 1986-1993 (Box 7)
    - Internal Revenue forms and related (Box 7)
    - Real estate material (Box 7)
- Branches
  - Branch 6: Announcements of programs (Box 8)
  - Branch 7: Minutes 1974-1984 (Box 8)
  - Branch 11: Announcements of programs 1998-2008 (Box 8)
  - Branch 137 (Arlazaroff Branch)
    - Yearbooks and directories, anniversary booklets 1944-1978 (Box 8)
    - Announcement of program cards, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Branch 593 (Brenner-Truman Branch): program, announcements 1982-1989, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Combined branch materials 1991-1992 (Box 8)
- Publications
  - Anniversary history: "50 years of Labor Zionism in Detroit 1906-1956" (Box 8)
  - Labor Zionist Organization of America: Yearbooks 1947/1948-1948/1949; anniversary celebration program, 1981 (Box 8)
  - Habonim Dror yearbooks 1968-2009 (some gaps) (Box 8)
  - United Jewish Folk Schools graduation books 1950s-1960s (Box 8)
  - Other organizations programs: Hashomer Hatzair, 1962; Pinsker Progressive Aid Society, 1977; Pioneer Women/Na'amat, 1982 (Box 8)
  - National materials: convention programs (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous
  - Partial autobiography of I.A. Liebson entitled "Not So Long Ago; Memories of My Life" (Box 9)
    (Liebson was active in the Detroit LZO)
  - Scrapbook containing clippings regarding activities 1974-1980 (Box 9)
  - Videotapes (VHS)
    - Tavor Video: Joey Nussbaum 1994 (Box 9)
    - Beit Lessin (Box 9)
  - Sound cassettes
    - Mayor Coleman Young Dinner June 17, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Afro-Asian Institute: Yehudah Paz -- Voice and Pulses (Box 9)
    - Histadrut Dinner: Leon Cohan Tribute April 2, 1987 (Box 9)
    - Histadrut function October 1977 (Box 9)
    - Rev. Jim Lyons: Remarks on a two week trip to Germany January 25, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Leon Cowan function November 18, 1987 (Box 9)
- Photographs
  - Panoramic banquet photograph of Arlazaroff Branch 137 -- J.N.W.A. Dinner Dance at the Detroit Leland Hotel November 24, 1934 (Folder 1)
  - Panoramic banquet photograph of the Jewish National Workers Alliance, Eleventh Convention, Detroit, Michigan May 1, 1928 (Folder 1)